[Music]
thank you
foreign
[Music]
tribe
tarun Yash
smoking
Negi ykx gamer Alpha GK workout
Mr Giga child of India
VNT Max
foreign
and lots and lots of other people I hope
you're doing all doing well sketch with
sneha sushant Malik boom Shankar boom
indrajit and lots of other people
good evening good day all of you so uh
let's go into the questions as always
and uh
today I will take a few more history
questions these days it's all it's all
been geopolitics a lot of geopolitics so
let's take some history questions today
but uh we will start with some questions
about geopolitics about what's happening
right now so
question number one
uh it's by two people Akshay and the
subham Dr Jay Shankar openly criticized
quad partners for not endorsing India's
map will the quad reach its objectives
if the West treats India in this manner
and what's your opinion about Dr Jai
Shankar's recent statement about what
quad countries not respecting India's
opinions in India's map while expecting
India to accept their opinion and views
on Russia Ukraine conflict so that's the
way it's always been the West sets the
rules and India and the Eastern Nations
need to just abide by the rules and do
whatever we are told to do right and uh
so they expect so we know what the quad
is the quad is this grouping of four
nations which is India the United States
Japan and Australia now you know what my
favorite term these days is it's wasall
state so uh Japan and Australia as we
know are U.S was all states Australia is
essentially a U.S owned Corporation or
company it's owned by the US and Japan
is under permanent U.S military
occupation so the quad essentially is
India and the US and a couple of U.S
what else so the two Nations that really
matter are India and the US in the quad
and in the quad
and and the quad is well it's viewed in
a variety of ways but uh one of the ways
that people view the quad is that
the quad is an anti-china grouping so
the major threat in Asia to peace and
security and stability is China we all
know that China is an expansionist
Nation with an imperialist mindset it
has a territorial disputes with almost
everybody in the whole world yes and uh
and especially all of its neighbors so
it's it's a big problem right and uh
it's it's a threat to China I mean China
is a threat to to Japan it's a threat to
Australia it's a threat to India and
it's a threat to U.S hegemony so so
these nations have come together and
they work in a variety of ways together
and the overall well objective seems to
be to to contain China in a way into you
know Safeguard each other's interests
now the quad like I said it's India and
the U.S grouping of Nations so they
expect India to abide by what the U.S
calls the so-called rules-based World
Order which is the whims-based world
order of the US whatever they decide
today is the rule is is the rule by it
so they expect India to fall in line
with U.S foreign policy
vis-a-vis the Ukraine Russia conflict
they want India to condemn Russia and to
oppose Russia and to to exceed to all
the sanctions that the West is has
imposed on Russia and to support Ukraine
in a variety of ways yes and India has
steadfastly refused to do that
so uh so the coordinations uh they are
in disagreement with India vis-a-vis
India's uh foreign policy with respect
to Russia and Ukraine right
so uh and they have been pressurizing
India most of the US has been doing so
and indirectly implicitly there is a you
know uh an acceptance of the U.S stand
from the perspective of Japan and
Australia as well so recently I think Dr
jashankar was asked the question about
the quad or something like that I don't
know what the context was but he said
that uh he he made the statement that
the the those Nations that don't even
endorse India's map want us to have the
same position as them in the Ukraine
Russia War
so he said that if if India does not
meet the expectations the if India does
not meet every expectations of the west
then it's fine we are not bothered about
it tough luck to the West that's what Dr
Jessica said and as we know the U.S
does not even accept India's map right
the U.S is actively arming Pakistan the
U.S is actively bolstering Pakistan's
military capabilities right now
yesterday the Secretary of State uh
blinken he tweeted something he tweeted
that uh what did he say he he tweeted
condolences or support to India on the
occasion of the of 26-11 the anniversary
of the Mumbai terrorist attack which was
carried out by Pakistan
and he tweeted out the message of
support or condolences or whatever and
it's so hypocritical that on the one
hand they are opposing terrorism and on
the other hand they are actively arming
the one nation that is the world's
epicenter of terrorism
yeah and an outright terrorist regime
whose only objective is to destroy India
so that's the kind of hypocrisy that the
U.S has been indulging in essentially
forever
and that's why there is a great deal of
skepticism when it comes to India the
way India views the US and its
pronouncements like I keep saying focus
on actions not on Words the actions are
like we support India we condemn
terrorism that's the words but the
actions are that they are arming the
terrorist Nation
and obviously they do not even uh accept
India's uh map of its territory right
now some portions of India's Northern
regions some portions are currently
temporarily occupied by Pakistan and
some by China
so if you look at the official U.S maps
they show India in a truncated form so
they don't don't even accept India's map
map right they don't endorse they don't
endorse India's map but they want us to
endorse their positions and accept their
positions and have the identical
position as them in a variety of things
right so that's what authorization spoke
about and it's it's good that he
clarified this
that the West cannot expect India to
accede to all their demands and to meet
every expectation that they have of us
it's not going to happen we have to work
in in a together in some kind of manner
that is mutually beneficial but don't
expect us to foreign fall in line with
your demands
it's not not going to happen so yeah
that's what this was about it's a good
statement
okay
psr3 and Shaheen have this question
China ghosts India from the first Indian
Ocean Forum meeting what's happening
China recently hosted the first meeting
of the Indian Ocean region whatever on
development and cooperation with 19
countries
according to reports China did not in
the invite the major Indian Ocean region
India and this is part of China's
strategy to limit India's influence in
the region how can India respond to
China's action
okay let's take a look at okay let's
take a look at first of all the Indian
Ocean region geographically let's
understand what this region is
so this is the Indian Ocean region
whenever we look at take a look at the
map of India and its uh surrounding
regions we are looking at the Indian
Ocean region so the Indian subcontinent
dominates the Indian Ocean region as you
can see it goes it protrudes thousands
of kilometers
into the Indian Ocean region it
dominates the entire region and the uh
other nations in this region are
obviously the subcontinental Nations
Pakistan Sri Lanka Myanmar Bangladesh
Maldives Etc of course we also have
Malaysia and Thailand and Indonesia we
have Australia over here we have various
uh island nations like Mauritius
Sensations which you're not able to see
here but they're there Madagascar and
the entire eastern coast of Africa and
also the uh the Nations the Eastern
nations in the Arabian Peninsula like
Oman Yemen maybe even UAE if you want
and a country like Djibouti perhaps yeah
so this is the Indian Ocean region and
this that's what this is all about right
now what happened what are we talking
about China and all that so China
recently had a meeting with a bunch of
Nations yeah
let's put a news report on the screen
so 19 countries attended China for China
forums Indian Ocean region meat and
India I was absent India was reportedly
not invited according to informed
sources yeah
so which nations did China invite I'm
sure there's a list somewhere here
otherwise I can list it out so if the
Chinese invited uh the Indian
subcontinent Nations like Sri Lanka
Pakistan Bangladesh
Myanmar the Maldives Etc it also invited
Nations like Indonesia and Iran
and other subcontinental nations that
are not
they don't have a coastline like Nepal
in Afghanistan then you had Oman as well
then you had Seychelles Mauritius and
Madagascar the island nations
and then Nations along the South the
African eastern coast like Djibouti
Kenya Mozambique Tanzania and South
Africa and Australia as well and
apparently there were representatives of
three international organizations also I
don't know which organizations these are
and the Chinese chose not to invite
India according to so what they are
calling informed sources
so uh
and this this uh whatever this was this
uh event was hosted by Lou Lou Zhao Hui
the former Vice foreign minister and the
former ambassador to India
so uh what's happening the Chinese
obviously have geopolitical Ambitions in
the Indian Ocean region
of late of the in the past decade or so
their Navy has been active more active
in the Indian Ocean region let's go back
to the map
so uh so and they they uh as we know
they have uh acquired certain Naval
bases in this region one is the Sri
Lankan Port of hambam Tutta here it is
which the Chinese have acquired on a 99
year old year lease
this was done when Mr rajapaksa was in
power yeah it's always easy to do such
things when a corrupt person is in power
I mean there are allegations of Mr
rajapaksa was um was allegedly corrupt
and very much pro-china
so one such asset is the other asset is
the Pakistani Port of guadar over here
which is close to the Iranian Port of
chabahar and the third one is the is is
a naval station or whatever it is in
Djibouti Djibouti City
which is at this strategic choke point
between the Gulf of Arden and the gull
and the Red Sea yeah
so the Chinese would like to start
dominating in the future the Indian
Ocean region now as we know their
superpower Ambitions have recently
encountered significant setbacks yeah
it's the economy is not growing and lots
of other things have happened but they
still will try to do everything they can
to keep on pushing those ambitions
so they want to
create some some kind of understanding
or cooperation between all the nations
of this region and exclude India because
the major nation in the Indian Ocean
region is India India considers
um if you listen to the words of the
Indian foreign Ministry and other
government officials India considers
these uh the Indian Ocean region to be
its so-called strategic backyard and
China wants to encroach into this region
so that's what's happening it's
interesting that Nations like Australia
that are part of the quad chose to
attend this meeting and obviously
Nations like Sri Lanka and Pakistan
obviously needs to be expected so that
is what is happening right that's what's
happening now we also have to understand
that there are other organizations in
the Indian Ocean region one is the
Indian Ocean Rim Association of Nations
which is uh which is essentially led by
by India
so this is a niche this is an
association that has I think 23 member
countries yeah this Association
comprises 23 member states and nine
dialogue partners and China is one of
the dialogue Partners yeah
and some organizations have a research
uh have uh Observer status
so this is essentially led by India to a
certain extent the first summit was held
in 2017 in Jakarta the second one was
held in Abu Dhabi in the UAE in 2019 and
since then this organization doesn't
seem to have been very active at least
no Summits have taken place of course as
we know we had the coronavirus pandemic
which started in late 2019 and after
that things did not well the entire
world order was disrupted so maybe
that's one of the reasons why it's not
happened so China seems to be attempting
to create a parallel parallel kind of
organization which is a rival to the
Indian Ocean Rim Association yep
that is the geopolitical tug of war that
we are witnessing
and that's what this was all about so
this organization the Indian Ocean Dream
Association
is to a large extent led by India so
that is the geopolitical situation the
Chinese are still not giving up I mean
why would they give up yeah they want to
they would like to have more Naval bases
they would like to restart the what they
call it what do they call it the uh
Maritime silk route uh initiative that
that created in conjunction with the Bri
initiative they're built in Road
initiative whatever the quality up so
the so that's what's happening so China
or so on the one hand we have bricks on
the one hand we have bricks Brazil
Russia India China and South Africa in
in bricks there are three major Nations
that really count India Russia China
and lots of nations are now applying to
join brics so bricks could be greatly
expanded by 2025 2026
but for bricks to be a viable
organization an organization that
actually works for that to happen India
and China have to work together India
and China have to find some common
ground to work together
if India and China are they continue to
have this extremely greatly adversarial
relationship then brics is a non-starter
brics is like you know it's not gonna
work
and yet we are seeing China uh doing all
these things
you know trying to intrude into the
Indian Ocean region trying to create a
parallel organization in parallel to
what India has created
so India and China are not going to be
what what would colloquially be called
friends India China are going to be
Rivals even if they can manage their
differences to some extent India and
China will remain Rivals as long
as China occupies Tibet like I've said
in the past the real solution to the
China India issue rivalry enmity
whatever you want to call it is Tibet
and China knows this very well if Tibet
becomes free again then India and China
will not no longer have any enmity
India and China are enemies because
there is a shared border which is
currently under marketed because China
has steadfastly refused to demarcate the
Border
and China has been indulging in all
kinds of provocative actions along the
border in other places as well and now
this is another I would consider this a
provocation
I'm sure the Chinese have a legitimate
right and interest in expanding their
footprint in various parts of the world
but as we know the Chinese peaceful rise
is anything but a peaceful rise so India
will have to keep a very close eye on
Chinese activities it's good that
Australia was part of it postural is
also part of the Quad so they can keep
an eye on what's happening within this
Chinese uh initiative this meeting of
the Indian Ocean region whatever it is
yeah yeah so we will have to keep a
closer on this and India and China are
the relationship is not improving uh
anywhere as much as people would expect
it to yeah recently Mr Modi and Mr she
they interacted briefly in Bali in
during the G20 Summit so there seems to
be a minor thaw at least the two leaders
are now talking to each other greeting
each other you know
uh so the relations really knows dived
after the uh the galwan incident in
which the Chinese provoked the Indian
soldiers in 20 Indian soldiers died in I
don't know how many Chinese died 40 60
80 100 whatever lots of Chinese died
and uh yeah so the relations have been
really bad since then now there seems to
be a slight thought but and yet India
simply cannot trust China the Chinese
would like to encroach in all spheres of
Indian influence and
and essentially try to erode India's
geovoltical influence so that's the
situation right now and it's not a big
surprise that this has happened
okay
okay Daniel Nicholson says if we could
add new member states in brics would it
be feasible to militarize Bricks Like
NATO if so this could lessen could this
lesson temporarily for about two decades
frictions between members like India and
China by increasing military cooperation
as India needs peace time for at least
another decade to push for the 10
trillion dollar GDP mark
see uh let's talk about NATO NATO is
dominated by just one nation what is
NATO it's the North Atlantic Treaty
Organization it's it's the U.S and the
nations of Western Europe
so in NATO there's only one major power
there's only one major pole it's the U.S
NATO is U.S is the U.S and its vasal
states in Europe
in Europe there is only one real power
which is the U.S it's not Germany it's
not France it's not Italy it's not Spain
it's not something else in Western
Europe there's only one real power
military and economic power which is the
US
so NATO is entirely led by the U.S NATO
is a proxy for the U.S that's why and
and everything that happens in NATO is
dictated by the U.S whatever economic
policies they have whatever military
policies they have
the U.S has nuclear weapons on the
territory of several uh European nations
yeah
which are all members of NATO
so it's entirely led by the U.S and
that's why it's a military Alliance in
the case of brics we have three major
Nations India China Russia
and India and China don't have a good
relationship it's been a terrible
relationship India and China have gone
to war
twice 1962 1967 62-39 Chinese 167 India
win India won and you're not taught
about it yeah
China and Russia newly went to war in
the 1960s the usuri river clashes the
Russians the Soviets had decided to Nuke
China and the Americans that saved China
that border dispute is right now
resolved but it will be reopened by the
Chinese when the deem that the time is
right so China and Russia don't have the
best relationship they are cooperating
and collaborating right now because they
need to but it's not a great
relationship so in brics we have three
centers of power brics is not dominated
by one by one single nation
it's uh the Chinese would like to
dominate brics but if India and Russia
work together then they can counter
balance China and breaks so within brics
there is all this friction
and India and China are essentially
enemy Nations
so you cannot have a military Alliance
within brics it's simply not feasible
how do you expect it's like expecting
India and Pakistan to have a military
Alliance and India in the militaries of
India and Pakistan to co-cooperate and
collaborate in a variety of ways it's
simply a non-starter it's not going to
happen it simply can't happen
so that way similarly like that India
and China simply cannot work together in
a from a military perspective there is
zero interoperability between the
militaries of India and China they are
designed to oppose each other so it's
not possible it's not going to happen
it's even if you add new member states
or whatever the three major power
centers are going to be India Russia and
China
yeah you can add Saudi Arabia to it
Saudi Arabia has very good relations
with India and even China but India and
Saudi relations are very good
so but Saudi Arabia is not a major
military power they are a U.S facile
state right now they would like to end
that sort of uh relationship they would
like to become more independent so all
sort of uh such uh aspirations are right
now in play from various Nations
Indonesia wants to join brics uh turkey
would like to join brics one years and
there are many other nations yeah but
even if you expand it it's not going to
be a military Alliance it's going to be
an economic Alliance at best
so yeah because of the India China
relationship the the Hostile
relationship and the and the bad history
it is impossible to militarize brics
it's impossible to turn it into a
military Alliance that can only happen
when this Coalition of Nations or any
Coalition of Nations is led by only one
nation then you can have a military
Alliance so brics is not going to be a
military Alliance as far as I can see
it's simply not possible
okay
descended of rigvedic Clans says please
discuss the southern Arc paper it
disproves many pseudo claims of
Western Academia propaganda it disproves
many things okay let's discuss and and
the other question is by VV the southern
art paper by David Reich has challenged
the step okay the step as the homeland
of the proto-indo-european languages
do you think this will lead researchers
to consider the out of India Theory or
perhaps other theories as more
convincing does Dr neeraj research on uh
Indian origin of R1 a have any
consequences will it have any
consequences on settling the
proto-indo-european Homeland debate okay
what is this paper and what is the
debate about so the claim the debate is
about the origin of the Indo-European
people and their languages the
Indo-European languages
the Indo-European languages are a huge
set of languages
I think more than two or three billion
people in the world speak Indo-European
languages and it is hypothesized that
these this entire family of languages
originated in the distant past from just
one language and as people spread across
the Eurasian continent these different
languages evolved out of that because
these people were no longer in touch so
the languages evolved differently and
eventually they became the entire family
of languages that we see today the
Indo-European languages
and there are two theories obviously
when it comes to India out of India and
the Aryan Invasion migration tourism
picnic Theory so the dominant Theory
which your textbooks will teach you and
with your with your esteemed professors
will teach you is that India was invaded
by this white people white skin people
called the Aryans about 3500 years ago
it's about the origin of India it's
about the origin of you and your
languages in your culture that's what
the entire question is about
so the dominant theory is that
is the dominant theory is that Hinduism
and Sanskrit are foreign to India they
represent an invasive force a hegemonic
oppressive patriarchal misogynistic
evil
Force
so Hinduism and Sanskrit are the the
culture of evil Invaders that's what you
are taught
and that's what the entirety of the
Indian such as you know
citizenry is is made to believe because
of the education system
so now um so initially there was a this
uh hypothesis that there was an invasion
then they could find absolutely zero
evidence of any invasion
so then they changed the hypothesis to
claim that it was a migration it was not
an invasion it was a migration
and yet there is no evidence to even
prove a migration so then so they are
stuck right now
so uh the one of the hypotheses
so what happened is that in recent times
in the 21st century in the first decade
in the second decade they began
archaeologists begin to find evidence of
an invasion but an invasion in Europe
a very rapid and drastic and brutal
invasion of Europe from the East
and as a result of this invasion you had
this Sudden Change in the cultural uh
in the culture that is represented in
the archaeological record and you had a
sudden abrupt change in the genetics of
Europe
so the original European genetics male
genetics disappeared and were entirely
replaced by this in the genetics of
these Invaders who came from the East
these Invaders
who came into Europe they came from the
East
which part of the East they say is a
Central Asian step let's take a look at
the Central Asian step what is the
Central Asian step
let's go to the map
so they found that see this entire
region is Central Asia from uh eastern
Ukraine up to Kazakhstan Kyrgyzstan
Tajikistan Uzbekistan Azerbaijan all
that stuff the uh north of the Black Sea
the Caspian Coast the Caspian Sea Coast
and up to yeah up to up to Kazakhstan
Etc that's essentially Central Asia
that's the entire Central Asian step
it's just grassland that's where nothing
else grows there so that that region is
called the Central Asian step
so uh
it's clear that these Invaders who came
into Europe and uh obliterated the
European male genetics and replaced the
male genetics with their genetics they
came from the East and it was believed
that they came from the Central Asian
step
so this this then became the dominant
Theory and then these people they were
given the term the name of yamnaya it's
a Russian word which means pit pit grave
or something
so that's not what they call themselves
that's what today's archaeologists and
historians call these people the yamnaya
Invaders of Europe
and it is said that that the yamnea also
were responsible for invading India and
maybe they represent the our Invaders
the thing is that the yamanea have a
different set of genes I mean they have
almost the same genetics obviously but
the dominant
patriarch lineage haplogroup is r1b
whereas the dominant uh petroleumal
lineage in India is it this is the
sister haplogroup r1a
hypothesis doesn't seem to make much
sense when it comes to India because we
have very little uh so-called genetics
in India
uh but yeah that's what it was so now
there is this new paper that has come up
so let's put the paper on the screen if
I can find it one second
he
um
where is it
just give me a thing all right here's
the paper let's put it on the screen
so this paper is called the genetic
history of the Southern Arc a bridge
between West Asia and Europe it is uh
the author it's got a bunch of authors
including Joseph lazari this uh other
people and in and obviously David Reich
so uh
structured abstract
what does it talk about
so let's take a look at this uh the
abstract so that you understand for
thousands of years humans have moved
across the southern Arc the area
bridging Europe through Anatolia and
West Asia we report ancient DNA data
from 727 individuals of this region over
the past 11 000 years which we
co-analyzed and with the published
archigenetic record to understand the
origins of the people we focused much uh
childcolithic and Bronze Age is about
7000 to 3000 years ago when
Indo-European language speakers first
appeared so there's an assumption that
you find a bunch of skeletons with a
certain kind of genetics and the
assumption is that they are the
Indo-European language speakers this is
an assumption there is no evidence
because there is no correlation
definite correlation between language
and genes I am speaking of foreign
language it's foreign to me I'm speaking
English but because I speak English it
doesn't mean my my genetics have changed
and they've become British or or English
genetics my genetics are Indian
subcontinent genetics that's what I am
right
so and today English is one of the
dominant languages in India so just
because somebody speaks a certain
language doesn't mean that that genetics
are going to reflect the genetics of the
place from which that language
originated so this assumption is deeply
deeply faulty
so they have found a bunch of genetics
in certain places and they claim that
this is the set of genes that is that
corresponds to Indo-European language
speakers
uh then the rational is the genetic data
are relevant for understanding
linguistic Evolution because they can
identify movement driven opportunities
for language spread we investigated how
the cultural changing language of the
the changing ancestral landscape of the
Southern Arc as reflected in DNA
corresponds to the structure inferred by
Linguistics which links Anatolian that
is hittite in luvian languages with and
Indo-European that is Greek Armenian
Latin and Sanskrit languages they had to
put Sanskrit but they put at the end
as twin daughters of a proto-indo
Anatolian language the results step
pastoralists of the yamnaya culture
initiated a chain of migrations linking
Europe in the west to China and India in
the east
some people across the Balkans about
five to four and a half thousand years
ago traced almost all their genes to
this expansion
step migrants soon mixed with locals
creating a tapestry of diff diverse
ancestry from which speakers of the
Greek paleo Balkan and Albanian
languages arose this is entirely
speculative but because once again you
cannot claim that a certain set of genes
is correlated with a language or a set
of languages
they should be talking about the
genetics of the yamna and the expansion
and the migration or whatever they found
they it's just wrong to correlate that
with genetics now with languages
anyhow let's go to the conclusion all
ancient Indo-European speakers can be
traced back to the yamaya culture okay
that's the conclusion they made whose
Southward expansions into the southern
Arc left a trace in the DNA of the
Bronze Age people of the region however
the link connecting the
proto-indo-european language speaking
with the speakers of the Anatolian
languages was in the highlands of West
Asia the ancestral region shared by both
and this is the genetic history of the
Southern Arc this is what they they
claim
so the the analysis that they have done
is genetic analysis
they have done analysis of ancient DNA
and on the basis of the analysis of the
ancient DNA and the results they found
they are making they are making drawing
conclusions about the spread of
languages and culture that is completely
wrong obviously they've put a caveat
somewhere in the paper that it is not
entirely going to be you know the
correlation is not causation and so on
so forth and the languages and genetics
are not entirely correlated they have
made that they've put that caveat in
there to cover their backsides but
overall they're making the claim of the
transmission of language and culture
through these genetics for which we
don't have any real evidence yeah
anyhow
but what's uh interesting about this
paper let me go to a lecture by David
Reich and put that on the screen because
that will help you understand better
what conclusion
uh they have drawn from this yeah
so thus far like I said it was believed
that the yamanea originated in in
Central Asia the Central Asian step
uh
so what are they claiming so this so the
southern Arc is an area divided
geographically between West Asia and
Europe which we Define as spanning the
culturally entangled regions of Anatolia
and its neighbors in both Europe and
West Asia of Cyprus Armenia the Levant
Iraq and Iran
so what they are saying is that now the
Aryan Invasion or the origin
so essentially the claim they are making
is that the origin of the Indo-European
people is not in the Central Asian step
it's in the so-called Southern Arc which
extends up to Iran
yeah so so
understand this let's let's put the map
on the screen and understand what this
means
we have always been told that the
white-skinned Aryans came from Eastern
Europe or Central Asia right that that
story has been around since the days of
what's his name uh Max Mueller
we have always been told that these are
white skin people who came from this
region
Central Asia and Eastern Europe now
based on the genetic evidence David
Reich and his team are saying that no
the Aryan Invaders they originated in
the so-called Southern Arc which is from
Anatolia
which is the major part of turkey all
the way up to Iran
so now the Aryans they came from this
region not from Central Asia
I have always been saying for for the
longest time that
what is the ancestry of the yamaya where
did they come from so now they are
attempting to answer that question and
the claim is that they came from Iran
now my question will be where did they
come from before that
obviously they did not spring out of the
soil in Iran or Anatolia they must have
come from somewhere else before that so
this is a story this is a
this is research that's in progress
the my major
the one of the major criticism is that
they have not they have completely
disregarded Indian genetics now we are
finding
genetics I mean um genetic information
from India as well the swath Valley the
Indus Valley the the Saraswati Hindu
Valley region and so on
um the so-called Indus periphery uh uh
genetics that they've found in other
places but which are closely related to
Indian genetics and so on it doesn't as
far as I have seen there is no uh those
pieces of genetic evidence have not been
considered
while as far as I know in in this paper
so what needs to really be done is that
the major population Center in the Asian
ancient world was India
it was India and yet none the Indian
genetic component is not looked at all
so in the future what needs to be done
and this has to be done by Indian
geneticists is that they need to
uh they need to sequence more ancient
genetic data from India we have so many
ancient samples sitting in museums I
know most of them will be contaminated
contaminated because our archaeologists
don't know how to handle ancient bones
and all but I'm sure we will find new
sets of Bones remains ancient remains we
found some in sonali we will find more
in the Saraswati Sindhu region we need
to sequence the DNA from there we we
will find ancient DNA some of it will be
preserved
so that needs to be brought into the
picture to understand the origins of of
the people of India and the in in the
indo-european-speaking people what they
call the Indo-European swing people so
this uh this paper why is it important
because now it it uh changes the focus
of the origin of the Indo-European
people from Central Asia to the
so-called Southern Arc which now
includes Iran
now Iran is geographically
you may not see it this way because you
have been taught geography from a
certain perspective but Iran is
geographically part of this Indian
subcontinent it is uh
if you if you go west from from let's
say Rajasthan there is absolutely
nothing in in your way like mountains or
something that will stop you from
reaching Iran it's just one continuous
expanse so Iran I mean even if you see
my uh my podcast with Dr neeraj Rai
there is a podcast which I have on this
channel he also refers to Iran as being
part of the Indian subcontinent so if
the origin of the
Indo-European people is from Iran there
could be a significant linkage with the
Sarasota region as well so all of this
has been neglected so this is obviously
a work in progress but it's important
because now
the claim is gonna be that the uh the
Indo-European people which which is
colloquially called the Aryans the RN
Invaders the other innovators did not
originate from Central Asia or Eastern
Europe they originated in
this Southern Arc which is turkey
Anatolia and Iran and in the future when
more evidence emerges I'm sure the focus
will move further eastwards into the
Indian subcontinent it's going to happen
it's going to happen and so so it's
still a work in progress but that is
what this paper is about so now even
David Reich and his team are admitting
that uh yeah the origin of the yamnya
Invaders who invaded Iran is in the
southern Arc which includes Iran and in
the future let's see where it takes us
so yeah that's the deal that's what this
paper is about I have not gone into the
specifics in great detail but that is
the overall uh
the conclusions of the paper
the claims that it makes
okay not a gamer says how similar are
old person and Sanskrit as they both had
a common ancestor the Assumption
assumption made in this question is that
old Persian and Sanskrit had a common
ancestor
so where did this assumption come from I
don't really know maybe it's something
that is taught in textbooks and about
eminent professors and teachers tell us
this let's talk about how similar our
old Persian and Sanskrit
so how do we find out
um
what Sanskrit okay
in person so one of the best evidences
of old person is the based on encryption
inscription
inscription is a very famous inscription
by the Persian king dharayas the Great
and this place called behistam which is
now called based on it was earlier
called bhagistan
in portion
the old Persian language in that
language the name of this place was
bhagastan it is now called so let's take
a look at the base Stone inscription and
try to see if it has any similarities
with Sanskrit you may all think that you
don't know Sanskrit Sanskrit is some
very strange and difficult language
that's not the case you all speak some
Sanskrit if you speak in Indian language
it is guaranteed that you use a lot of
Sanskrit vocabulary
so
so you all actually know
Sanskrit not not spoken Sanskrit not
um
not conversational Sanskrit but you do
know Sanskrit vocabulary so now let's
take a look at the behestan inscription
let's take a look at the first uh
paragraph or whatever it is so this is
in the cuneiform script now what does it
say if you read it out
it says
so so this sounds like
like corrupted Sanskrit it sounds like
you take Sanskrit then you mangle it up
and you mispronounce some words and
that's what it sounds like so if you
were to speak it in proper Sanskrit it
would say was
foreign what does it
means I am
means we know what means in India but
for for the persons it meant King
means great king I am house the great
king
means king of kings
the King of Persia
means the the king of the dasu people
other other people who I Ruled my vasals
yes
foreign
and so on so he's recording his lineage
he says my Pita my father was with
father
's father was Arya ramna
and so on and so forth
so he speaks about his entire lineage
he's in the lineage lineage of his
dynasty of his ancestors starting from
the emperor haksha Manish the founder of
the akshamanesh dynasty the akaemini
dynasty so as you can see this is all
written in old person if you know
Sanskrit or even if you know Hindi or
any Indian language you will understand
to a certain extent what is being said
over here that is
the interesting part
so uh
so now the the question is which came
first which language came first did old
La old portion come first
did uh Sanskrit come first or are these
two languages sister languages and they
descend from an older language these are
the questions right now if you look at
the bahiston inscription
you will find that it sounds like broken
or corrupted or mangled Sanskrit it
sounds like an upper Branch language of
Sanskrit what are upper branchial
languages these are descendant languages
of Sanskrit these are corrupted forms of
Sanskrit so today's language is they
today's modern Indian languages the
so-called what are classified by
linguists as indo-aryan languages
these languages are descendants of the
old prakrit languages and the prakrit
languages are descended
from Sanskrit
right
and Bali is one of those practice
languages
so
and if you look at old portion it sounds
like a prakrit language or or an upper
branching language
so it is clear
it is clear I mean I'm sure lots of
linguists will disagree and I don't care
what they say
I don't care what they say yeah but it
is clear that this language old portion
is an upper branch of Sanskrit which
means a bunch of sanskriti speakers
migrated out of India they settled down
in Persia and over several centuries the
language changed
it became corrupted that's what happens
that's how languages have evolved in
India so old person is an upper brancher
it's a daughter language of Sanskrit
and you can see it sounds it looks and
sounds quite similar you can actually if
you know Sanskrit or if you know any
Indian language you will actually
understand much of what the rivals was
saying two and a half thousand years ago
right
so you can see the similarities so the
question is how similar are old person
answers with they are quite similar old
person and Sanskrit are they the
difference between them is like the
difference between Portuguese and
Spanish kind of
uh to some extent like the difference
between English British English and
American English the pronunciations are
different some words are the words are
morals the same actually so in the case
of old person the pronunciations are are
different instead of saw you have ha and
some words are mangled the chatriya
becomes
and so on but overall you can understand
what that was saying you don't need to
know person you just need to know
Sanskrit then you will understand
everything that there was saying in this
inscription
so that's the answer very similar
languages old person was a descendant of
Sanskrit not a sister language they did
not both have a common ancestor the
ancestor of old person was Sanskrit
itself that is the deal all right so
that is the answer to the question
okay Akshay says what are your views on
Graham Hancock and his latest Netflix
series ancient apocalypse and YK says
have you watched Graham Hancock's
ancient pop a couple apocalypse Netflix
series what do you think of it I hope
future seasons of this will cover
ancient India as well okay so I recently
did go ahead and watch
this uh series
so I have spoken about gram Hancock
before uh I think he is an important
scholar and researcher in history in
ancient history
um he puts forth the perspective or the
or the idea and based on a lot of
evidence that human history is not what
we are taught it is it's much older than
what we are taught
and uh so he puts for the different
narrative based on different uh
perspective not narrative perspective
based on genuine evidence but some of
his claims obviously seem a little
far-fetched one of the claims that he
made is that there was a like like the
title says ancient apocalypse that
happened about 12 13 000 years before
today
um called the younger dryas event
and now we have found evidence that this
actually happened this actually happened
it was an apocalyptic calamitous event
most likely caused by a meteor strike or
a strike of a comet or or multiple
fragments of a comet or meteor they have
found evidence of this now there is a
meteor
um buried under the ice in Greenland
that they found which corresponds to
this date and there's other evidence as
well so yes many of his claims are
actually uh based in in facts and they
have been corroborated
so he should be taken seriously so and
now he has come up with this series
called ancient apocalypse
and I went ahead and watched it it's
seven or eight episodes all about 28 30
minutes long so what do I think of this
so let's first put this on the screen
the IMDb uh page for that uh series
ancient apocalypse
and let's take a look so so it's a
pretty well reviewed it's got a 7.7 out
of 10 rating as you can see it seems
people seem to like it let's take a look
at the episode guide so that we can
speak for further about this
so episode one is about a flood uh
Graham Hancock travels to Indonesia to a
place called gudang patang or something
to investigate a megalithic pyramid so
yes there is a pyramid there that seemed
to date back to its Origins date back to
about 23 more than 20 000 years before
today and so that once again forces us
to re-examine history that if if a
structure is more than 20 000 years old
we have to revisit the way we look at
history
the in the past first of all in the past
when the ice age was in full force the
sea levels were significantly lower and
many
land masses existed that are now
submerged for instance the whole of
Indonesia was a massive gigantic
landmass connected to Asia
connected to India yeah today it's all a
bunch of islands at that time out of the
landmass and there's so much that has
been lost in its it's submerged Under
the Sea so yeah that's so that's what
this was about then there is a
then he goes to Mexico there are
pyramids in Mexico ancient pyramids
there's a the tradition of quotes the
civilizing hero yeah that's what's
mentioned here who came after a big
flood so there is this flood myth
everywhere in various parts of the world
which speaks about a great flood that
destroyed almost destroyed the world and
then things and then Humanity started
again after that then it goes to Malta
where there are these megalithic temples
one of which is called gigantia and so
on he speaks about that it's orientation
with the star Sirius
and all that he speaks about that uh
then he goes to uh the Bahamas the
Bimini structure and uh he shows that uh
oh there also there was much of it was
above water what is now submerged under
the water and there is a massive
megalithic structure over there called
the Bimini something or the other
then he goes to go back to pay in in
Anatolia where you have this 11 000 year
old uh
uh
structure or or
yeah it's it's a it's a megalithic
structure in in government and it's not
alone there are a bunch of other
structures around it which date back to
almost 11 12 000 years ago so once again
and and these were apparently
deliberately buried for some reason
so he speaks about that over there
um then he goes to North America there's
a Serpent Mound he speaks about how
Native American culture has been
systematically destroyed and erased in
very little of it survives now and yet
some of it survives like The Serpent
Mound which which once again
is aligned with certain uh celestial
events like the solstices and all that
then he goes to Turkey where there are
certain underground cities which is very
interesting which could have been
bunkers designed to survive some kind of
apocalyptic event
and he then he goes to North America
where you have the channels cab lands
which seems to be a massive geographical
terrain which was created by a enormous
flood
maybe at the end of the last ice age
maybe the flooding happened because of a
meteors meteor strike on ice sheets and
all that so I watched the entire thing
and I find see all of it is interesting
definitely interesting he may make some
very good points but his major thesis is
extremely flawed his major thesis his
major Central claim is that there was
one single ancient civilization before
the before the great flood which seems
to before the younger dryas event which
is about 12 30 000 is before today
so his major Central claim is that
before this event the younger dress
event there was one single Advanced
civilization in the world
and after the younger dress event and
the flooding or whatever happened then
this one culture Advanced culture
somehow somehow survived to some extent
and they sent
civilizing Heroes to various parts of
the world and that's how you have the uh
the tradition of
in in Central America and Osiris in
Egypt and various other civilizing
figures who come from nowhere and
civilize the people teach them how to do
Agriculture and teach them culture and
laws give them laws and all that
in one of the so his claim is that there
was just one Advanced civilization I
don't know why that claim is being made
why were they not seven or eight
different Advanced civilizations before
the younger dress event
I mean the Earth is a huge Planet there
are so many different continents and
land masses so why only one Advanced
civilization that sounds very abrahamic
to have just one God or one in one
civilization that that later gave
civilization to the whole world to the
whole world after the world was
destroyed uh during the uh or or put it
thrown into turmoil because of the
younger dryas event
so that is one
claim that doesn't make a lot of sense
to me why keep on insisting on just one
Advanced simulation that civilized the
whole world later
that sounds very much like the white
savior narrative that the white people
went and saved everybody and civilized
everybody so that
claim that is being made has no basis in
effect
the other uh all the other evidence that
Graham and cook shows us it is actual
archaeological evidence
the interpretations are all subjective
obviously but the central claim is not
based in any evidence at all it has no
factual basis it's just
something that he seems to believe the
second thing which I did not like is
that there is no mentor of India India
is the oldest civilization civilization
that the entire world knows of
it's the oldest continuously existing
civilization in the world and the oldest
known civilization in the world that
dates back almost 10 000 years and maybe
much most likely much it's much older
than that
Graham and Cox studiously avoids India
he none of the episodes covers India and
uh
in one of the episodes he speaks about
the the seventh episode about turkey
in which he goes to Cappadocia and other
places he speaks uh he says that in the
past there was a
once again there's a there's a lag all
right
this seems to be
lag buffering
let it return and then we'll talk about
this
is it still buffering seems to be a lag
lag lag
um
no better is it
no better somebody saying no better
okay I think it is better now and I'm
gonna continue
so the thing about Graham Hancock is
that he completely avoids India which is
incredible
it's an enormous Omission he also
entirely omits Africa there is nothing
in Africa Africa has its own culture its
own civilizations its own kingdoms and
Empires
completely ignores Africa he completely
ignores India as well
in the seventh episode which is about uh
turkey he refers to Zoroastrianism as
the world's oldest religion
he speaks about these illustrian or
Persian tradition of the first human
being called yema y I am a ima who then
civilized he he refers to yima as a
civilizer hero well the Persian yema is
nothing but the rigvedic Yama which we
now call yamaraj
so in this in the Indian rig Vedic in
The Vedic tradition
the first human being was Yama
actually there were two human beings
twins Yama and yummy
Yummy Yummies was a twin sister of Yama
and these two siblings were the children
of Surya the son
yeah so that is the tradition that's the
that's the Vedic tradition in the
portions also follow this relation
because they were they came out of India
so in Persia also they have the
tradition of yima they don't call him
Yama they call him Yama so Graham
Hancock speaks about this he refers to
yima as a civilizing hero
is the oldest possibly the oldest
religion in the world he totally
sidesteps the fact that it all came out
of India
so these are there are major holes
in in Graham Hancock's perspective maybe
it's deliberate he completely ignores
the largest continent in the world
Africa nothing there
and he completely ignores the oldest
civilization in the world India
so and and lots of the many of the
claims he makes are based on on leaps of
imagination and uh yeah so
so much of his work is interesting it is
certainly important but his conclusions
and his claims are many of them are
fantastical
his claim of an ancient civilization one
single ancient civilization which was
very Advanced it's it's based on no fact
or data at all yeah and
and clearly even though he is
open-minded he is married to an Indian
lady Etc in a origin lady and he speaks
about all these things he says that the
archaeologists and the historians have
been misleading us and they have this
very dogmatic notion of things but he
himself
seems to exhibit the same Tendencies of
dogmatism of avoiding India and Africa
and all that and and many of the
conclusions he draws are not really
based in fact so that's the kind of
mixed review I would offer I would offer
to you about Graham Hancock and his work
and especially about this uh new series
that he has come up with yeah it's it's
okay it's it's interesting to watch but
I was really
surprised to see that there's no mention
of Africa or India at all nothing at all
so clearly there is some
either either he is not focused on his
regions he's only focused on America and
some other places or maybe there's some
kind of bias but as a researcher who is
interested in the in the ancient world
and who has spent decades researching
what the historians have been hiding
from us how can you how is it possible
that you never ever tried to investigate
the history of India
so yeah there's something I don't know
fishy about this I don't know
so definitely somebody we should take
seriously to a certain extent some of
his work is indeed important it helps us
uh plug certain holes in in their record
of history and how we understand history
but yeah there are major problems with
graham Hancock's work so that's my
review of specifically this series
ancient apocalypse
says how ancient is Judaism so Judaism
is the religion of the Jewish people and
it is the official state religion of
Israeli of the nation of Israel where is
Israel I'm sure you all know but let's
put it on the map just in cases
just in cases
close the map
here it is
so where is the nation of Israel it's
this tiny little Nation on the east
coast of the Mediterranean Sea yes south
of Lebanon north of Egypt west of Jordan
and Syria
and uh yeah so that's the location so
Judaism originated in this region
in in what is now called Israel more or
less right so how ancient is Judaism
well the oldest record that we have of
Judaism or of the Jewish people
is from an Egyptian record it's it's an
Egyptian inscription that and it's it's
a Well historians are kind of divided
about whether it does actually refers to
the Jewish people or not but assuming it
does indeed refer to the Jewish people
this uh inscription is about 3100 or
3200 years old
so that's the if if it indeed refers to
Jews then that's how old Judaism may may
be maybe it would be slightly older than
that so maybe three and a half thousand
years
but the oldest record seems to be about
three thousand three thousand one
hundred years old
so if Judaism is about three and a half
thousand years old
yeah
then it would be approximately as old as
the civilization of China
and uh
uh they have a significant extensive
history you heard Kings like David King
David King Saul
um King Solomon Etc
and so on and then uh you had this
region that was it was it was invaded
and occupied and ruled by the Romans
then there were the revolts against
Roman rule by the Jew by the Jews in
retaliation the Romans destroyed the the
Temple of Solomon in yerushalaim in
Jerusalem and so on so yeah there's a
whole history that the Jewish people
have and then you had the Crusades then
you had the the Islamic expansion in
this region and that they took over the
region and in the Romans uh they forced
many of the Jews to to move out of the
region the Jewish diaspora went all
across Europe because of the Roman
policies and all that they were forcibly
expelled out of the region then you had
the Islamic occupation of the region
then this region became entirely Islamic
entirely Muslim more or less the Jews no
longer had the presence there for the
longest time so for the longest time
there was no Israel and then Israel was
recreated at the end in the first half
of the 20th century by European powers
by mainly by by Britain Etc there's a
whole story in that so that's when
Israel started existing again
so that region is the original homeland
of the Jewish people this dates back to
about 3000 years maybe three and a half
thousand years but for the longest time
there was no Israel there was no nation
of Israel there was no nation state of
Israel
that was recreated about a hundred I
mean less than 100 years ago so that is
the story of the Jews in in very brief
it's a it's a very complex and long
history
but yeah to answer the question Judaism
is about three thousand maybe three
three and a half thousand years old at
the most as far as we know from whatever
evidence we have all right
okay says congratulations on fire thank
you very much so uh can you talk about
the slavery of Europeans by is by the
Islamic Ottoman Empire
how extensive was this slavery of
Europeans how many Europeans were
enslaved in total
I don't think many many people speak
about this and yeah okay all right
so uh the
Ottoman Empire obviously had this policy
of of slavery they engaged in the slave
trade lots of people were taken as
slaves mainly from Africa and also from
Europe
so uh what are the origins of the
Ottoman Empire the original of the
Ottoman Empire are the um Invasion and
occupation of Anatolia by the Turks
so the Turks uh let's go to the map
so the Turks where the turkic people of
Central Asia their origin most likely is
in eastern Asia in the Mongolia region
maybe the new people that the Chinese
spoke about were the possibly the
ancestors of the turkic people we also
had turkic people who ruled parts of
Northern India the Turkish Hindu Shahi
dynasties who are all Hindu of course
yeah and they actually initiate they
actually defended India for a couple of
centuries from turkic invasions despite
being turkey of turkey origin themselves
anyhow
the Turks first started intruding into
the region of Anatolia which was
historically Greek about roughly 900 or
a thousand years before today right
um and then over time they made more
inroads into the place and eventually
they were able
uh one of the major incursions into this
region happened when the Turks were
fleeing the expanding Mongol Empire so
so in the 13th century 14th century
there was a sudden new phenomenon in
Central Asia in eastern Asia the Mongol
Empire emerged out of nowhere under the
leadership of the great Genghis Khan and
the Turks were running from that and
that's that's how one of the major
encouragement to Central Asia happened
into Anatolia but the Turks happened
under Suleiman Shah if I'm not mistaken
and later obviously uh at that time you
had the Byzantine Empire of this region
which was the Eastern uh Roman Empire
and eventually the Turks were able to
conquer Constantinople it is now called
Istanbul and so on
and then you had the Ottoman Empire
which was based out of Constantinople it
was also the ottoman caliphate the
turkey the Turkish Sultan was also the
caliph right and they had this practice
of slavery which was perfectly legal in
their culture
and many of the slaves
that they many of the people they
enslaved where the Europeans themselves
so first of all Anatolia was
historically a Greek region it was
Christian at the time
and when the Turks started coming into
Anatolia they uh they had this policy
they had this culture of bride
kidnapping so if if a young Turkish man
Turkish man wanted to get get married he
had to prove his manhood and his in his
ability as a warrior to by by going into
by going into in a neighboring Village
and kidnapping a girl and bringing her
back and then he could marry her that
was a custom
bride kidnapping it still exists in many
parts of the world including in
Afghanistan and Pakistan I believe yeah
bright kidnapping so this was one of the
Customs they had so when they started
coming into they started uh occupying
Anatolia they continued this tradition
they started kidnapping girls the local
girls and marrying with them in over
time the turkic people who were
originally Central Asian and they looked
like Central Asians or Mongols they
became completely europeanized so if you
look at the people of turkey today they
look like Europeans they mostly have
Anatolian Greek blood or maybe Armenian
Georgian blood
region right so it's all because
primarily of this of this custom of
taking
um you know kidnapping Brides so that
you could consider to be one of the
manifestations of of taking a person as
a slave because you're kidnapping
somebody in getting married to that
person that person essentially becomes a
slave for life so that is one thing then
they obviously had the slave trade they
It is believed let's take a look at some
articles right some some scholarly
articles otherwise uh
it's best to take a look at some
scholarly articles so here is one
uh European slaves in the Ottoman Empire
Christian slaves Muslim Masters white
slavely slavery in the Mediterranean the
Barbary Coast in Italy 1500 to 1800
so that's a book from 2003 that is one
um
and I can also show you a review of that
which is if it would ever load it will
load here
European slaves in the Ottoman Empire
it's a review article and so on and
there are many other other books that
have been written about this in articles
written about this so this was indeed a
thing it was indeed something that
happened so it is believed that uh
in the in the Black Sea region
over a period of about between 1500 to
about 1800 or so the Turks took about
two and a half million European slaves
and the Turks also had this practice of
uh
they had this Elite armed
Force called the janissaries
so the janessaries were entirely made up
of slave boys
so the Turks had conquered parts of
Europe including the Balkan region
Balkan region and all
um and parts of other other Europe other
parts of Europe as well so what the
Turks would do is that they would force
every household in these regions to to
offer one to give one boy as a slave to
the Turks it was not offered it was
taken yeah so this was a custom it was
called the blood tax or something I
forget the Turkish division or something
they call it yep so all of these
families in these regions they had to
give away one boy as a slave to the
Turks
and it would be young boy maybe probably
most likely less than 10 years old some
some of them would be older but they
would all be young pre teenage boys most
likely
most of them these boys would be taken
as slaves and they would be uh converted
to to the religion of the of the Turks
which is Islam they would uh be offered
education
in the Turkish language
and they would be converted into
soldiers
these soldiers were called the
janessaries
and um this was also slavery and the
janessaries were the elite Bodyguards of
the Turkish sultan
so that's how deeply they were
indoctrinated and they were they became
fanatical in the support of the Turkish
Sultan one of these boys was taken as a
hostage as a slave
was a
was Prince Vlad of valakia
who was later known as Vlad the Impaler
so he went on to escape or somehow
Turkish captivity and he became one of
the major uh
opponents of the Turks in Romania
he was later called Vlad the Impaler
he's also known as Vlad dracul or
draculia which is
from where the entire Dracula story
comes from yeah
so yeah that's an interesting historical
nugget yeah
so yeah the Turkish uh slave trade was
very extensive they also they also used
to purchase slaves from the Barbary
slave Traders
which was in the North African region
the Mediterranean region the Pirates
these two you know
raid ships and raid the coasts and all
and take slaves and then sell these
slaves to the Turks
uh that's how it was
there was a time when in Istanbul in in
concerned in Opel about 20 percent of
the population was made up of slaves and
many of them were of European origin
yeah
so overall I think hundreds of thousands
of people would take Europeans were
taken as slaves in the in the North Sea
region not not not see the Black Sea
region It is believed about two and a
half million Europeans were eventually
taken captured by the Turks and and
converted into into slaves so yeah this
is not really spoken about a lot for
whatever reason but yes it was a very
very big deal
okay Evelina says what weakened the
ancient Indian Society internally that
allowed it to be conquered by foreigners
after such major developments as in the
field of Prosthetics
was it some kind of cultural degeneracy
like in the West Was India after peaking
uh suffering cultural decline like in
the west today is it a cyclical nature
of civilization was or was India immune
to this westerners say that women come
to positions of leadership when Society
declines
uh well it depends on the culture and
all that see uh what weakened Indian
Society internally that allowed it to be
conquered by foreigners it was not a
weakening of Indian society that caused
it to be that that allowed it to be
conquered by foreigners
in any society in any any civilization
there are these cycles of of
consolidation of political power and
fragmentation of political power
so in India we had various Imperial
phases
um
entire Empires that spanned the entire
continent subcontinent and unified the
entire subcontinent you have the mauryan
Empire that unified the entire
subcontinent politically just one ruler
the Emperor of India whether it was
Ashoka or whoever else one emperor of
all India that was doing the modern era
then also during the kushan era when you
had a great emperor like kanishka who
ruled over the whole of India and much
more yes almost all of India and much
more Beyond India so once again uh
consolidation of political power across
the entire subund continent then you
have the Gupta Emperors who also unified
the entire continent subcontinent
politically so whenever India was
unified politically it was impossible
to invade
before the mauryan Empire you had the
Nanda Empire the Nanda Dynasty
in the Nanda dynasty was in power in
India
over unified India when the Greek
warlord Alexander the Greek tried to
invade India and we know what happened
you know what happened his soldiers
rebelled the mutinied against him they
said we will not go further east because
we know what's waiting for us the entire
might of the Indian empire the Nanda
Empire the Greeks would have been
obliterated so whenever India was
unified politically under a single
leader under a single Emperor India was
impossible to conquer
and there were times when these Empires
fragmented and then you had political
instability you had lots of different
kingdoms
fighting little petty fights against
each other that's when it was
easier to invade India yeah
so and there have been multiple
invasions in conquests of India by
various foreigners so you had the uh
you had the Greek invasion of India
which was subsequent to Alexander's
Invasion this was in the post-seleucid
era so you had various indo-greek Kings
who ruled in in gandar in Northwest
India some of them made in roads further
east and so on but they all absorbed
Indian culture they assimilated into
Indian culture and their descendants
still live in India today nobody knows
who knows who was Greek culture Greek
and just you're not I think most people
in northern and western India will have
a fractional amount of Greek ancestry
maybe one person two percent possibly
yeah
were of Indian origin they lived in in
the kushans lived in what is what was
then called
and the skitians they roamed all across
uttaramadra Central Asia these people
had Indian ancestry and their culture
was very similar to Indian culture so
they also assimilated very harmoniously
into India it is only in the past 1000
years that very foreign cultures came
into India and they tried to destroy
Indian culture
so the reason for the reason
so India obviously was advanced in the
field of Prosthetics in in in in
mathematics in astronomy in science in
all kinds of things
and and in in arts all those things that
is of no use if you don't have the
military strength in the in the
political ability to defend the nation
and in the in the subcontinent
so you may have the best culture in the
world the most advanced science in the
world but if you are not unified
politically and strong militarily all of
that is going to be
lost
so that's what happened to India so it
was not a weakening of Indian Society or
a fault of Indian culture it was just
the unfortunate fact that the Invasion
the turkic invasions happened when India
was not unified politically
and that's why all of this happened
there was no cultural degeneracy in
India the cultural degeneracy entered
India in the past 1000 years
through foreigners
yeah so there was no cultural degeneracy
it is just the the fact that India was
India was caught at a time India was
invaded by the Turks at a time when
there was no political Unity you had
various kingdoms that ruled India in
various parts of India but there was no
single unified Center of power like an
emperor like you had when the homes
tried to invade India during the time of
the Gupta Emperors skanda Gupta Etc and
it was not successful successful as long
as the Gupta Empire existed so that's
that's the reason there was no uh
weakening of Indian Society or or
cultural degeneracy in India you I mean
one of the things that said here is that
westerners westerners say that women
come to positions of leadership when
Society declines in India it's not been
the case in India women have been in
positions of power and it's not been a
symptom of the decline of society it's
been a simple symptom of the strength of
Indian Society in Indian culture in
Indian culture women I have the highest
risk respect in regard and women have
historically taken positions of
leadership they have even fought Wars
and battles and all that in the past
so in India if a woman is in a position
of power it's not a symptom of of the
decline of society or degeneration of
society it's just it's a symptom of the
strength
of Indian Society that's a whole
different thing right
saurabh says is Mahabharata post-mortion
history
as per our great historian Madam romila
she says that yudhisthir got inspiration
from the great king Ashoka
uh yeah it appears that she did actually
make the statement let's take a look we
need to put some evidence on the screen
for this to be taken seriously so what
did the great lady romila thapar say
so this was I think in 2019 or so
and uh yeah there are some clips of this
uh which are available on Twitter
so uh history gold from the great
historian Romina thapper maybe
yudhisthir in Mahabharata had the image
of Ashok in his mind when he renounced
his kingship
so that's what Romulus said in this
video clip I'm not going to play the
clip over here
but that's what she actually said romila
thapar has been portrayed as one of
India's greatest and most eminent
historians she has written authored
various books that are still taught
in uh College University or whatever
level and she said that maybe yadishtir
of the Mahabharata
had the image of Emperor Ashok in his
mind when he renounced his kingship
now Ashok obviously was a morian emperor
of India he lived in whatever BC 232 BC
or whatever it is I don't remember the
exact date but yeah
let's say what is said here is correct
and he lived in 232 BC the Mahabharata
comes way before that
way before that
so in the Mahabharata there is there are
mentions of the river Saraswati so
obviously the Mahabharata thing the
event of the Mahabharat happened when
the Saraswati was still an active River
and not a gone dried out desiccated
river right
happened thousands of years before the
memorial era when Ashoka when Emperor
Ashok ruled India
and yet this lady this great imminent
historian made the claim that maybe
yudhisthira of Mahabharata was thinking
of Ashok
when he renounced his kingship
so yeah that is something that the lady
indeed said and I have no
logical explanation for what she said it
makes no sense to me it I'm unable to
understand or fathom the thought process
or the logic or the chronology
so yeah obviously the Mahabharata is not
post more in history
modern history is very recent history
it's like day before yesterday it's only
two and a half thousand years before
today in in the big picture perspective
of Indian history it's like day before
yesterday
the Mahabharata happened several
thousand years before that so yeah
that's one of the great statements of
this great eminent lady madam
yeah
incredible
okay Maine says have you watched the
interview of Salvatore babones at India
today where he claims that it is not the
foreign institutions that are anti-india
but it's the Indian intellectuals that
are anti-india
but I said me that foreign institutions
are also anti-india so what's your take
on this
it's very interesting so this gentleman
bones he I think is Australian of
American origin or something I don't
know what his background is I have not
seen the entire interview I've seen some
clips here and there and he indeed said
that you know the major enemies of India
are the Indian intellectuals themselves
he said that it he said that it's not
the fault of Western institutions
for being for for drawing various
conclusions there are anti-india it is
the fault of Indian intellectuals
that this image of India has been
created right he said it's the fault of
the Indians
not the fault of these institutions in
the West in the surveys that they create
and all that yeah the problem with this
statement is that all these surveys
are created by the are are done by the
West
there are various surveys of of Human
Rights situations and happiness indices
and democracy indices and all which are
entirely run by the by the main to the
Americans and by various Western Nations
and Western institutions it's not done
by Indians right
has done he has exonerated all these
institutions and laid the blame on the
Indians these Indians who then go on
social media and parrot whatever the
Western surveys are saying these Indians
are merely hired coolies
that's what they are I will not take
anybody's name because I don't want to
yeah that's not that's not important but
the Indians who then put it out on
social media and you know publicize it
they are nothing but hired minions hired
coolies sepoys yeah that's what they are
but the samples of these surveys are
selected by these by the agencies by
these institutions right there is the
the pew pew Group which can which
conducts research on uh I don't know
what languages and religion and caste
and human rights and whatnot
that that's not run by Indians yeah
so this uh statement that was done by
these days Mr baboon has become baboons
has become very popular
uh all Indian podcasters and journalists
are interviewing him he's become kind of
a celebrity Etc but he is very cleverly
exonerated the Western institutions that
are at the core at the root which are
the root cause of all these
all this into India sentiment right
so I find it very interesting
it's like
there are various uh
western intellectuals part who are
either professors or their members of
think tanks or whatever that kind of
take a pro-india position but at the end
of the day they are still exonerating
the West there are various such people
some of them are quite subtle about it
and some of them are just open you know
in your face
so Salvatore baboons is in your face
he he he's taking a very crude approach
and he's really enjoying the attention
he's getting right now yeah he's become
kind of a celebrity and you know Indians
Indians are very happy to adopt if
somebody says a couple of good words
about you Indians become all happy and
emotional about it yeah this is our guy
we need to promote him and blah blah
blah one has to be careful you have to
observe a person for at least five years
minimum before you can trust that person
that's something Indians don't
understand
the moment somebody says two good words
about you you are like ah let's go and
embrace this person
very emotional people Indians and that's
why Indians are so easy to fool so easy
to fool anyhow
okay two questions here one is by Mangal
uh how and when did Indians start living
in Guyana
and the other question is by kuldeep
I have recently been to Amsterdam and I
came across some Indian looking people
who I came to know were not indians but
surinamis
they look similar to us even their food
their Customs culture ethnicity is very
much like us
but it seems that there were contract
laborers of slaves during colonial times
so can I discuss the ancestry of the
suriname's people so first of all okay
good question very nice let's first look
at the geography of the region to
understand what we're talking about
Suriname and Guyana the question is
about these two Nations
let's go to maps
maps maps maps
so where is Suriname where is Guyana
it's in South America on the Northern
tip on the North Eastern
part of
South America
so you have French Guyana over here
where you have the rocket launching
station which is run by the French Guru
then you have Suriname over here
and to the east or to the west of
Suriname you have this nation called
gayana
yeah
uh and grandma is also a cricket playing
Nation for instance yeah so what's the
story what's the history so in Suriname
you have people of Indian origin who
look like Indians they look exactly like
Indians yeah and their Customs are
Indian culture customs their food is
Indian food but they most likely speak
the Dutch language
so that's the deal in Guyana you also
have Indians and all lots of Indians
and then you have Trinidad and Tobago
and the West Indies nearby and we know
there are lots of Indian origin people
in the West Indies so what is the story
what is happening over here
that's the question let me put something
else on the screen
I'm Excuse me
so let's understand how this happened
how did these people end up over there
so
take a look at the cement this is
something I tweeted in 2017 the British
transported half a million Indian
endangered laborers which means slaves
to Mauritius they transported half a
million of such Indians to the Caribbean
region and Guyana
and 1.5 lakhs to South Africa that's a
million Indians forced into slavery cut
off from their Roots forever and this
image illustrates this this entire thing
so these are These Are the Voyages which
were forced upon Indian endangered
workers which are slaves
between 1835 and 1917. so the British
gave created this new terminology
indentured workers
to replace the term slaves but it was
exactly the same thing there was no real
difference
so when we talk about Suriname and
Guyana
there's a half million Indians who who
were transported forcibly to this region
the west Indies which are islands
Suriname and Guyana
so that's that's the origin of these
people yeah
and uh
yeah so the British sent at least 1.5
lakh indentured laborers a fancy word
for slaves from India to South Africa
they had very few rights they were
subject to races laws racist laws for
generations and so on
so that is the answer to the question
that's how it happened
the British in the 19th century in the
in the beginning of the 20th century
sent nearly
a million Indians into slavery in
various parts of the world Mauritius if
you go to Mauritius it's full of Indians
of Indian origin people they speak the
mauritian Creole language which is a
mixture of mauritian language in various
other languages some of it will be Tamil
some of it will be Hindi some African
languages as well
so you have the Mauritius region you
have Seychelles in which the sessions
archipelago also has Indians many
Indians there we know about South Africa
obviously we know about the east coast
of Africa
and we have Guyana and Suriname in the
West Indies region now let's talk about
Suriname
let's go a little deeper into Suriname
I'm putting up a Wikipedia article on
the screen
as always let me remind you Wikipedia is
not always a trustworthy source of
information but we'll just keep it here
for the sake of convenience
so in Suriname there is uh the Indo
suriname's population many people of
Indian ancestry let's look at Suriname
itself and let's look at the
demographics in Suriname
do we have a section on demographics
here we have it
if you look at the ethnic groups in
Suriname the largest ethnic group is
Indians 27.4 percent of suriname's
people are of Indian origin
then you have maroon and creole and
Javanese 14 of the people of Suriname
are jawanese from Java Indonesia
and the French considered the French
rulers in this region they considered
the Jawan is also to be Indians but
today they are considered to be a
separate category right
so yeah so
the largest the largest ethnic group in
Suriname is Indians and the current
uh the the current
president of Suriname is of Indian
origin let's put this gentleman's um
page on the screen his name is chandrika
Prasad santoki
chandrika Prasad santoki who is a
suriname's politician former police
official police officer the ninth and
current president of Suriname right
so yeah he is of Indian origin
and also the same thing in Guyana lots
of Indians there so that is the deal
so that is the uh that is how these
people ended up in this Indian origin
people ended up in Suriname in Guyana
as indentured laborers essentially
slaves and now they are a significant
percentage of the population there and
they still continue to practice their
their culture and their Traditions to a
large extent many of them if you look at
the um
if you look at the religions that you
have in Suriname today let's take a look
at that I am sure Hinduism will be in a
minority because many of them will have
been converted to whatever other
religion exists there let's see religion
the large see Indians are 27.4 percent
of the surinamis but Hinduism is just
18.8 percent and Christianity is the
major religion in Suriname more than 52
percent
so yeah no surprise there that's what
happens
anyhow if you look at the Hindu
surinamis and Hindu Guyanese people they
are more Indian or more Hindu than
Indian Hindus themselves they have
preserved their culture better than it
is preserved in most parts of India
today which is strange but not
surprising
okay this is by Val who says come on
come on
the Native Americans were not exactly
all peas Flowers and Butterflies they
were blood thirsty tribes who practiced
human sacrifice and were murdering each
other in their Wars for resources just
like any other people on Earth it just
happened that the stronger tribe came
and took their land the American natives
which is the Europeans the American
natives would have done the same if it
had been vice versa so this gentleman
person I don't know who it is is
claiming that the Native Americans were
cruel bloodthirsty barbarians who were
sacrificing humans and maybe sacrificing
children and murdering each other they
were just brutal primitive Savages and
the Europeans came and they were
stronger and they civilized them that is
the narrative that we are seeing all
across that has been the dominant
narrative for the past several centuries
yes
the Western narrative The eurocentric
Narrative the white supremacist
narrative that all non-white
non-european people were blood thirsty
barbaric Savages who needed to be
civilized
who needed to be civilized and they were
killing each other they were practicing
Human Sacrifice one of the things you
know one of the easiest ways to make
somebody look like a barbarian is to
claim that they've practiced Human
Sacrifice so what were the Europeans
doing in the Middle Ages what was the
the second most popular book in Europe
in the Middle Ages was the malayos
malefica room
the Hammer of the witches
it was a
a Christian book
it it was a manual about how to identify
which is how to torture them and how to
kill them
and the Europeans killed hundreds of
thousands of women
by burning them at the stake
in the name of religion in the Middle
Ages in Europe is this not human
sacrifice it exceeds any Native American
Human Sacrifice even if it existed on
by several orders of magnitude and what
evidence do we have that the Native
Americans practiced human sacrifice and
they were murdering each other and they
were bloodthirsty
nonsense these people push you know so
let's take a look at what actually
happened
so I have on several occasions said that
the Europeans killed about 100 million
Native Americans and people don't
believe it so let's take a look at what
are the
academic consensus seems to be
so here is a research paper from 2019
yeah
quaternary science reviews Earth system
impacts of the European arrival and
great dying in the Americas after 1492.
so
it estimates that the European arrival
in 1492 led to 56 million deaths by
1600.
in just a century 56 million deaths
in in the Americas and some of them they
claim is because of diseases no diseases
and all that so this is one research
paper
there is another uh another
article here from CNN European
colonizers killed so many Native
Americans that it changed the global
climate researchers say
and this once again goes according to
the 56 million deaths figure yeah
so this is larger than any Holocaust
anything that Stalin did anything that
Mao did in just a hundred roughly 100
years and obviously there was much more
to it than this I am pretty sure that
the actual figure I still haven't done
uh put forth collated all the all the
figures which have been put forth by
various research groups and all that
maybe I will do that in the future I am
pretty certain that the figure actually
exceeds 100 billion people in a period
over a period of a baby two three
centuries in just a hundred years you
have 56 million deaths let's add another
200 years to it and then come up with
the actual figure it's going to exceed
100 million
so these Europeans
they killed more than a hundred million
Native Americans
can you imagine that
and yet they they come on this channel
and they claim that the American the
Indian Americans or Native Americans
were to blame they deserved it there
were primitive Savages
they practice human sacrifice what
evidence do you have nothing but yeah
you'll make the claim and there were
murdering each other for resources
so if there is some kind of intra inter
tribe conflict you're gonna portray it
as murder what about the history of
Europe over the past 1000 years
it's a history of murder bloodlust
Warfare constant War
the first world war and second world war
where European tribal conflicts
which which ruined half the world
the most bloodthirsty
people
on the planet are the Europeans look at
their history
look at what they've done to each other
what they have been doing to each other
you know Joseph gobble said that you
should always blame your enemy of what
you are of what you have been doing
I don't know what the exact quote is I'm
not going to open up the screen and put
that on the on the screen but yeah
accuse the other side of what you are
guilty of
so that's that's the kind of Mind Trick
these people play so they have the
Europeans have been responsible for the
most horrific genocides in the world
only the Turks come close to it
what the toxicity did in India would
possibly exceed 100 million deaths yeah
so the Native American genocide is is
something similar and yet they have the
gall to come here and say that they they
the Native Americans deserved it because
they were bloodthirsty apparently and
primitive and backward and they
practiced human sacrifice and they're
murderers so it's fine it's fine it's
fine what happened this is the narrative
that has been the dominant narrative for
more than a century
ever since the the
for for a couple of centuries at least
ever since the age of colonialism began
so they colonized the world they
destroyed the world they plundered the
world they couldn't connect to genocides
in at least three continents and then
they accused the other side of being
primitive and barbaric and that's why it
is Justified
so that's what we have been up against
all this time now it will change it's
it's high time
that we put for the truth
okay Russia says I recently came across
many articles which say that the Russian
military doesn't use the brahmos missile
the reason cited was that they already
have the p800 Onyx missile which India
has redesigned to create the brahmos to
which degree is it Russian the brahmos
how much has India added to it and why
does Russia not use it
okay
I'm sure we all know what the Brahma
picture looks like let's take a look at
brahmos what does the brahmos missile
look like
do you want to see what it looks like
let's do that let's put that on the
screen
so here's a simple image search for the
brahmos
and here's what the missile looks like
from the side
uh here's another view of the brahma's
missile another one here's the brahmos
missile taking off and so on and so
forth so this is the overall appearance
of the brahma's missile
now you are referring to the p800
missile right
so let's see what the p800 missile looks
like
it's called the Onyx missile
so if you look here it looks very much
like the brahmos facile and the the fact
is that the brahmos missile
has been uh
created constructed design whatever
based on the design of the p800 Onyx
missile
so that's why the brahmos looks very
much like the p800 and the Russian
military has the p800 Onyx missile and
it's been used in various conflicts
including most likely in the Ukraine
conflict as well
now the brahmos missile is a more
advanced version of the p800 Onyx
how much of it is Russian how much of it
is Indian we don't quite know these
this these facts will not be revealed to
the public this this is classified
information it's not available for
public consumption so yes it's a jointly
developed missile Indians and Russians
Indian scientists engineers and Russian
scientists engineers have collaborated
in in creating the brahamas missile it
will be a more advanced version most
likely of the p800 Onyx
uh and so on right so that's what it is
now why does the Russian military not
use
the brahmos missile well the Russian
military doesn't use the brahma's
missile because they already have the
p800 Onyx first of all and secondly
because they have other missiles as well
for instance they have the three they
have the Silicon missile the three M22
sircon missile which
is a scramjet-powered maneuvering
anti-ship Hypersonic cruise missile so
the brahmos missile is a ramjet-powered
maneuvering anti-ship
supersonic cruise missile the brahmos
missile has a top speed of maybe Mach 2
or Mark III yeah two or three times I
think it's two times the speed of sound
so it's a supersonic missile maybe two
and a half times the speed of sound so
maybe Mach 2.5
the Zircon missile is a Mach 9 missile
it travels at nine times the speed of
sound
right it's a Hypersonic missile and it
doesn't use a Ramjet motor it uses a
scramjet motor a super uh supersonic
combust combustion motor
so the Russians have more advanced
missiles
and that's why they they most likely
that and because they also have the p800
Onyx missile and the Zircon missile in
various other missiles that's why they
maybe have not maybe that's why they've
chosen not to use the brahmos missile
thus far there have been reports that
some of the brahmos muscles will be
inducted in some of the various uh uh
Russian naval assets maybe destroyers or
whatever
so we're not sure if it's a tap if it
has happened or not but the Russians
have multiple alternatives
now we are obviously uh designing we are
there's a new there are new variants of
the brahmos missile in development right
now including a Hypersonic version
including a smaller version including
there's a whole bunch of missiles that
are currently in development maybe maybe
they have developed maybe they're not
these of matters are not publicized
so that's all that happening uh so the
Russians have lots of options and
Alternatives and that's why they have
not inducted the brahmos as far as we
know in their military
so yeah they have options and the Zircon
missile is a very interesting missile it
seems to be a missile that nobody has
any defense against it's a Mach 9
maneuverable missile so it's not a
missile that will go Tower in a straight
line it will maneuver like the brahmos
does the brahma's muscle is a
maneuvering missile it can do this
s-shaped pattern while cruising over the
over the sea it can also
dive suddenly from from a height so if
you have a Chinese military station on
the other side of a Himalayan peak then
you can launch a brahmos missile that
goes above the peak and then Dives 70
degrees down at a 70 degree angle so the
brahmos is a maneuvering missile the
Zircon is also maneuvering is missile
but it is it it Maneuvers at Mach 9
incredible speed
I believe there is no missile defense
system in the world
that can defend a Target against the
Zircon missile
so whatever aircraft carriers the
British have the or the Americans have
they have no defense against the zircon
they could defend themselves against the
brahmos possibly
but not against the Zircon so the
Russians have more advanced missiles and
that's why most likely they have not
inducted the brahmos and I would say
that India should
possibly try and acquire some of the
technology or some of those missiles the
Zircon for instance because you can't
have you can't rely
on just one missile obviously we are
coming up with various new variants of
the brahmos missile but we should have a
whole
family of missiles for different users I
mean if you are a carpenter you don't
have only one tool in your toolbox right
you have a whole bunch of tools right so
we need to diversify our portfolio of
missiles obviously we have a whole big
portfolio of various kinds of ballistic
missiles we do have that no doubt
we are also um we have the shorya
missile which is a kind of hybrid kind
of missile we also have the nearby
missile which is a subsonic cruise
missile that is under development and
which seems to now uh being now doing
well in tests and all that
but we would also want to we should also
invest in Supersonic and possibly
Hypersonic missiles
yeah so yeah we should do that
all right
wipe off says turkey has released images
of its new fifth generation fighter
aircraft which is currently in the
fabrication phase
and it will be completed in March 2023
while we Indians are still waiting for
AMC accs approval what are your thoughts
I am sad seeing everybody going ahead of
us
okay I'm not sure what is the state of
the amca it's obviously
the amca is the Indian future fifth
generation fighter aircraft the advanced
medium combat aircraft which is
currently under development
I'm not sure what the exact status is
the Turks are developing their own fifth
generation fighter plane they've
released some pictures of that of that
and it is currently in its fabrication
phase the first prototype will be
completed in March 2023 according to
what is being said over here okay I'm
not sure about that maybe it will
I believe that the first prototype of
the amca will be ready in 24 or 25. a
couple of years after the Turks and the
first test flight of the amca will
happen soon after maybe 26 27 I don't
remember the exact time frame but most
likely by 2030 or so the the
first of fighter aircraft AMC could
interpret production possibly around
2030 or so see when you are developing a
newer shot it takes time look at the
development time period time frame of
the F-35 fighter plane which the
Americans have now inducted it took more
than 20 years it cost almost a trillion
dollars
so any new aircraft that you're
developing especially Advanced aircraft
like fifth generation fighter planes it
takes time
maybe the Turks started before us and
all that's fine it doesn't matter so I
don't think India is lagging too far
behind what India needs to do is that is
India needs to first of all start
inducting more of the pages in fighter
planes yeah fighter jets
uh
and we need to
push on with the development of the amca
maybe the if maybe the uh t e BDF twin
engine deck based fighter possibly
for the Indian Navy for the for the
aircraft carriers because we already
have two aircraft carriers
I have always been against inducting
more aircraft carriers but since we
already have two we need fighter planes
that can you know that can be uh used on
those aircraft carriers so we should
have our own indigenous fighter plane
for that so I think there's one of that
in development the te dbf twin engine
deck based fighter plane and the amca
will most likely be ready hopefully by
the end of this decade by 23 2030
roughly that time period so I don't
think we are too far behind wait a
couple of years and we will have our
first prototype will be about 20 24 25
latest
so we are we are doing okay we're not
doing badly the thing is uh
the government should give full support
to this program and it's that's what's
happening we also have certain other
fighter certain other planes that are in
development unmanned aircraft
um
flying wing based designed aircraft the
the drdo aura or ghatak or whatever it
is called which is a very interesting
development you know fully completely
fully stealth stealth stealth aircraft
and all that so I think India is doing
well India is doing well there is no
need to become sad that the Turks have
gone to years ahead of us it's all right
it's all right what India needs is a
decade of Peace ideal two decades of
peace and we need to stop buying foreign
defense equipment foreign planes and all
that we need to start creating our own
um systems defense systems and all that
so yeah I think we are on track for that
we are doing well I'm sure we can do
better so let's let's see how it goes
but overall it's we are doing fine
okay
foreign
's Bridge Is it true that this name was
coined around the 18th century why is
the Rama setu linked to abrahamic Faith
I don't know I have no idea what
abrahamic faith and all that
but yes this structure has historically
for thousands of years being been called
the Rama setu it is the British who came
to India and named it the Adams Bridge
there is a mountain in Sri Lanka which
is called the Adams Peak
which the British it's a name that the
British gave
it was historically called something
else
Adam speak Sri Lanka let's see Adam
speak Sri Lanka
so it's called The Adam's Peak and and
what was it called historically in in
this Sri Lankan sinalis tradition
it was called the sripada
footprint of the Buddha or the footprint
of Hanuman or footprint of Shiva
and so on mountain of shiver's light and
so on but but it is the the British
given name that is now being used Adam
speak in Wikipedia The in Wikipedia it's
always the Western narrative that is
prevalent
I mean it's it's a foreign name it's a
name that has been imposed by Foreigner
foreigners so why is it not called
sripada or whatever else right
so that's the deal that's the problem
the entire world is still following
these eurocentric Traditions these
occidentalist Western supremacist
Traditions they have the Rama SATA which
is called the Adams Bridge we have the
sripada which is called Adam's peak in
Sri Lanka
we have Sagar Mata which is called Mount
Everest
we have the Sea of saurashtra or the
Indian Sea which is called the Arabian
Sea even the Arabs call it the Indian
Sea if you look at Arab Chronicles in
the Arabic language the sea was always
called the Indian Sea
but now it's called the Arabic Sea
Arabian Sea then you have the the Champa
samudra which is now called the South
China Sea which is given the Chinese a
great you know pretext to claim the
whole place the entire sea for
themselves and there are so many other
other examples of that
uh
so yeah so the it is the the
westerners that have imposed all these
names and
we have been forced to to
use these names so it is high time we
decolonize it is high time there are so
many names in India place names names of
places of cities and towns and Villages
and Roads and other landmarks which are
named after Invaders and after the
Europeans
or Jim Corbett National Park Jim Corbett
was a killer of tigers he was a poocher
why have we named this National Park
after that Barbarian
Jim Corbett
and there's this McLeod ganj somewhere
and there are so many such names then
obviously there are all the names named
out of the turkic occupiers of India we
need to decolonize it is high time we
start the process of decolonization
but yeah some of it is happening which
is good
um for instance in in Mumbai there used
to be this Prince of Wales Museum Prince
of Wales Museum which is now called the
chatrapati shivaji Maharaja vastu sangra
halai or something like that excellent
very good I like it so we need more of
this we need to rename and of course
there is this there was this road in
Delhi which was called the aurangzeb
road now it's called the Kalam road
again excellent so this process needs to
happen there are so many names that are
false are wrong
and we need to reclaim our history yeah
so yeah it needs to happen it needs to
happen
pranab says how can Sports influence
Society according to you how India lost
its own sports and embraced foreign
sports how can India influence through
four Sports how can Sports influence the
society see uh let me give you an
anecdote
I remember when India won the 2007
2020 World Cup in cricket
it was there was an outpouring of
Jubilation Nationwide
on the streets you had complete
strangers who were embracing and hugging
each other
so you know what sports does Sports
unifies and not sports but sporting
success unifies a nation
because when the nation succeeds
everybody wants to take part of in the
success and claim some credit for the
success
so when the nation succeeds everybody
wants to be part of that but when a
nation fails in something the blame
gaming Blame Game and finger pointing
starts so nothing unifies a nation like
success and nothing divides the nation
like failure so one of the easiest ways
of of raising the morale of the of the
nation and unifying the nation is to
achieve sporting success
and that's something the West
understands very well that's why they
invest so much in sports that's what the
Chinese have understood that's what the
Russians the Soviets is to understand
India has traditionally neglected Sports
very badly now India has started to
become good at sports in certain sports
like say wrestling in badminton this is
the rise of India is is beginning now
it's still in the initial phases
um
so Sports can influence Society greatly
it can create an entire ecosystem uh
it can create hundreds of thousands of
jobs you know sporting staff coaches
trainers Sports Medicine professionals
ground staff there's a whole
job market that can be created by
investing in sport yeah
and people who are athletes when they
retire they can go and become part of
the job market and offer coaching
another another specialized services to
Future athletes and emerging athletes
and children and all that so it can
provide lots of jobs but most
importantly Sports unifies the nation
let's say I mean right now you're the
football World Cup happening India is
has not qualified for that but imagine
if India were to qualify for the
football World Cup and maybe reach the
quarter finals or semi-finals it would
re it would unify the nation like
anything because you will have
footballers in the team in the 29 member
team that are from all parts of India
lots of footballers from the Northeast
because the Northeast is very good in
football Manipur in other places and
Kerala as well and Bengal so there are
certain states that are really good at
it but other states are also represented
so you'll have sports people from the
entire nation and they will all be doing
well together imagine how well it will
unify the nation whenever the team does
well
so Sports can be a great unifier it can
also provide lacks of jobs
so yeah that's the importance of sports
and it's it's a it's a crying chain that
the Indian government has for decades
neglected Sports and a loud sport
sporting associations and federations to
become deeply corrupted I'm not going to
name anybody any particular organization
but yeah we know what happens yeah there
are different
Sports
some major sports some not so major
sports but they all have their
associations and federations and many of
them as has been have been alleged to be
deeply corrupt
and that's and who suffers as a result
it's the athletes that suffer and it's a
nation that suffers so yeah that's how
it is and obviously we have our own
sports like kabaddi like Coco and
various martial arts and all which have
all been lost because of the foreign
occupation of India in the past 1000
years
some of the sports still exist like
kabaddi kabaddi can become a worldwide
phenomenon if we invest in it properly
in various other nations also play
kabaddi obviously all the nations in the
Indian subcontinent including Iran play
kabaddi well I think Iran are the
defending Asian Games champions in male
as well as female kabaddi and they beat
India in the finals in both these uh
disciplines which was very
which was unfortunate you know anyway so
the Iranians play well kabaddi well the
Sri Lankans also played the bangladeshis
the pakistanis Afghans I'm not sure but
maybe they do also yeah so it's a
subcontinental sport India and Persia
are the main powers but yeah if we had
our own sports and we we have lost some
of those
we should revive them
and we should invest in them it's great
and it keeps Society fit and healthy so
that's an added bonus and benefit
all right
um
Karthik says your thoughts on Alex
Pereira knocking out Israel at the Sanya
so he's talking about MMA mixed martial
arts the UFC the Ultimate Fighting
Championship in which in
which weight class was it I don't
remember light heavyweight perhaps so
you had the Brazilian Alex pahira who
knocked out Israel at the Sanya house
from Nigeria if I'm not mistaken in in
the Sanya as the defending was the
defending champion and he was almost
unbeatable and this guy from uh from
Brazil who is an indigenous Brazilian
not a not not a transplant from Europe
so Alex pahira is belongs to one of the
Brazilian indigenous tribes
and he is a very good fighter he's a
kickboxer
Ada Sanya is more like a MMA fighter but
uh Alex Paradise is a kickboxer so he
came into this fight it was a five round
title match in the last round he knocked
out Israel at the Sanya it was a
stoppage and yeah it was great it was
great to watch I was supporting Alex
Pereira and I'm glad he won so yeah I'm
not I don't know how many of you watch
it but I am a fan of martial arts I
watch UFC I watch MMA I watch uh
Bellator if it's available and so on so
yeah it's it's good fun to watch
uh saurabh says do you play chess what's
your rating and what's your favorite
opening I do not play chess anymore I
used to play checks chess as a kid and
as a teenager and the last
serious chess game I played was more
than 20 years ago more than 20 years ago
so I no longer just play chess and the
reason is that chess is extremely time
consuming I used to be good at chess but
it is incredibly time consuming a single
chess game game can take two three hours
and I don't have the kind of time so I
that's why I quit chess I don't know if
I had any rating I never played at a
elite level what was my favorite opening
I think it was the
Queen's Indian defense I'm not sure I
don't know what it's called but yeah one
of those was my favorite opening and
yeah it was it was good good fun to play
it so yeah chess is a great game it's
good for kids to develop their tactical
Mouse and mental mental acuity and all
that but it is incredibly time consuming
so so that's the reason why why I have
stopped playing chess and I've not
played a serious chess game in more than
20 years
okay let's take some live chat questions
live chat questions do we have any
questions if you have any questions I'll
take a few
um love martial arts yes I love martial
arts too and as you know I also practice
boxing not with opponents but against
the bag punching bag it's fun it's a
good it's a good way to stay fit and
also strong
okay let's take some questions about uh
or from the live chat
is there anything okay Quran says is
there anything more to discover in
mathematics I think there must be much
much more Discovery mathematics uh there
come there come phases in history when
people believe they've discovered
everything
like in the late 19th century I think it
was Lord Kelvin or whatever who said
that we whatever we was to be discovered
we've discovered and nothing more will
come out he was talking about physics
obviously and how wrong was he so
similarly for mathematics I'm sure there
is a lot more to discover yeah
um
how did Peter die I'm not sure no idea
um so much of what we know about
comes from the Raja tarangini of kalhana
who was a
historian from from Kashmir
and uh
I'm not sure if if it mentions the the
manner in which
died so yeah maybe I will look into it
and find out but as far as I know there
is no information as far as I know
your view on FIFA World Cup by Qatar
well we know that this world cup was
awarded to Qatar
as a reward for services rendered Qatar
is is a U.S was all they do I mean you
know they offer certain services to the
U.S geopolitical services and various
things and
and in
recognition of these Services as a
reward for for obedient service they
have been given this world cup and it's
going on right now it's not the best
place for a World Cup it's a very hot
place and they have used almost what
what you could consider to be slave
labor to build all those stadiums mainly
people from Bangladesh Nepal maybe even
India some of them and so on the human
rights situation that is terrible and
all and uh yeah so it's unfortunate that
this nation that has no sporting
tradition no football tradition has been
given the World Cup
and I'm sure there are many more better
deserving candidates but that's how it
it happens that's how it goes there is
one nation that rules the world it's the
sole superpower and they they
have they control most of the
organizations
whether it is geopolitical organizations
or sporting organizations and that's why
they can get these things done
and yeah that's how it is
so the World Cup is typically played not
in winter but this time it's in Winter
and I think the the English Premier
League had to be rescheduled because the
the World Cup has been being played in
the in the winter Autumn or whatever
so yeah that's that's what I that's
That's My Views about this
Andrei says how to be strong I expect
you mean physically if you want to be
physically strong lift weights lift
heavyweights and if you have no elephant
with before don't start with
heavyweights start with light weights
but if you want to be strong you have to
progress
progressively lift heavier and heavier
weights and once you start lifting
respectable weights like for instance if
you can deadlift 100 kilos then you are
then you are at a respectable level yeah
and you can consider you consider
yourself to be strong so to be strong
you have to lift weights you have to
lift heavy weights but if you're a
beginner Don't Drift heavyweights you
will get injured start with light
weights but yeah it's great fun lifting
weight is great fun
so that's how you get strong physically
mentally it's a whole different story
all right
Mr Giga chart of India says why do
Western historians ignore India well
why do you ignore someone because you're
you're jealous because see the truth is
that for the past three four centuries
they have been portraying the West as
the as the founded head of civilization
and the epitome of everything good and
civilized in the world and they know
that the most ancient civilization and
the most advanced civilization has
always been India
and if they start not ignoring India
then their lives will be exposed and
that's why they ignore India it's very
simple that's how it is
uh which language does the sinhalis
language Sinha language belong to well
if you ask any modern language they will
say that it belongs to the indo-aryan
language family which means that it's
not a southern Indian language it's
actually a language that has originated
in Northern India that's what they would
say and if you listen to people speaking
sinhalis it it sounds kind of like the
Marathi language kind of little bit to
some extent and so on
um it also does sound like Tamil to some
extent so yeah it's it's kind of like
that but it is classified as an
indo-aryan language
of course this entire
uh classification system of Indian
languages needs to be Revisited and
initial
this entire fakery of the dravidian
language family I mean come on so yeah
we need uh to revisit Indian linguistics
all right all right I think we are at
the end of today's session more than two
hours as always
so uh thank you very much once again for
your viewership and thank you very much
to all of you uh we have crossed
five lakh subscribers on this channel
it's all thanks to you I am extremely
very grateful to all of you for your
support
for your viewership and we will continue
this the channel is still in actually in
its infancy I'm still figuring out what
I want to do with the channel so thank
you to all of you I'm incredibly deeply
profoundly grateful and we will continue
this next week with next weekend's live
streams until then take care all of you
and I will see you very soon take care
thank you bye